Guide to the Judy Richardson Papers, 1963-2014 RL.10177
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Judy Richardson papers
1963-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Richardson, Judy
RL.10177
30 Linear Feet
Judy Richardson is a veteran of the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee who worked in Mississippi during the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project in 1964. She later worked with Blackside, Inc., on the Eyes on the Prize civil rights documentary series, and co-edited Hands on the Freedom Plow, about women's experiences in SNCC. Her papers include materials from her years working on staff at SNCC in Atlanta and Mississippi; her involvement with the Drum and Spear Bookstore in Washington D.C.; extensive print and audiovisual materials from her work in documentary film, including projects like Malcolm X: Make It Plain, Eyes on the Prize, and Scarred Justice: The Orangeburg Massacre; her correspondence and drafts from the editing of Hands on the Freedom Plow; project and event files from numerous committees, speaking engagements, and panels; personal files, including her FOIA about her SNCC service in the 1960s; and subject files collected from various projects.
Access Restrictions
The Hands on the Freedom Plow Series is closed to research until 2025 except by permission of the donor. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. The rest of the collection is available for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Judy Richardson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2014-2019.
Collection Overview
The Judy Richardson Papers include materials from her years working on staff at SNCC in Atlanta and Mississippi; her involvement with the Drum and Spear Bookstore in Washington D.C.; extensive print and audiovisual materials from her work in documentary film, including projects like Malcolm X: Make It Plain, Eyes on the Prize, and Scarred Justice: The Orangeburg Massacre; her correspondence and drafts from the editing of Hands on the Freedom Plow; project and event files from numerous committees, speaking engagements, and panels; personal files, including her FOIA about her SNCC service in the 1960s; and subject files collected from various projects.
Materials are arranged into series based on format and topic. The Hands on the Freedom Plow Series is closed until 2020. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use.
Historical note
Judy Richardson was born in Tarrytown, New York, and attended Swarthmore College before joining the civil rights movement in 1963. She worked for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee from 1963 to 1966, with posts in Atlanta, Mississippi, and Alabama. She worked for the Mississippi Freedom Summer Project and also coordinated the operation of a Residential Freedom School in 1965.
Richardson then joined the staff of the Drum and Spear bookstore in Washington, D.C., and spent several years serving as its children's editor and director (1968-1972). During the 1970s she also founded and managed the Maelezo Bookstore (1972-1973), worked for and later directed the Black Student Fund (1973-1977), and meanwhile took college courses at both Howard University and Columbia University. She eventually earned a degree in children's literature from Antioch College (1977).
Richardson joined Blackside, Inc., in 1978, becoming an advisor and then associate producer of Eyes on the Prize I and II, an award-winning PBS series on the civil rights movement. She also co-produced Blackside's Malcolm X: Make It Plain, another documentary. In 1982, she began working for the United Church of Christ's Commission for Racial Justice, writing commentaries and serving as its Director of Information from 1984 until 1989. Richardson worked for Blackside until 1999, serving as producer and education director. In 2001, she joined Northern Light Productions, and produced several historical documentaries and educational films.
Richardson co-edited Hands on the Freedom Plow: Personal Accounts by Women in SNCC, which was published by University of Illinois Press in 2010. She became a distinguished visiting professor at Brown University in 2012.
Civil rights movements -- United States; Civil rights movements -- Mississippi -- History; Documentary films -- United States; Documentary films -- Production and direction; African American women civil rights workers -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Booksellers and bookselling; Children's literature; Film festivals -- United States; Blackside, Inc.; Northern Light Productions; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party; Mississippi Freedom Schools; Council of Federated Organizations (U.S.); United Church of Christ. Commission for Racial Justice; Mississippi Freedom Project
- Hands on the Freedom Plow, 1995-2014; 1
  Access Restrictions
  This series is closed to research until 2025 unless permission is granted by the donor.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes drafts, edits, and correspondence between Richardson, her fellow editors, and the book's contributors over the ten years of work prior to the publication of Hands on the Freedom Plow: Personal Accounts by Women in SNCC (published in 2010 by University of Illinois Press). The materials have been arranged into three subseries: Drafts/Editing; Publication; and Correspondence.
  Drafts/Editing includes work by the volume's six editors: Faith S. Holsaert, Martha Prescod Norman Noonan, Judy Richardson, Betty Garman Robinson, Jean Smith Young, and Dorothy M. Zellner. All of the editors are SNCC veterans who solicited contributions from other women who joined the SNCC organization during the civil rights movement. The subseries includes name files for each contributor, including several contributors who were not published in the final version of the volume. The files typically include both the original and subsequent drafts written by each author for Hands. This subseries also includes the editors' work in writing introductions and transitions between each segment and chapter of the text.
  The Publications subseries largely consists of marketing and publicity files leading up to and following the book's publication in 2010.
  The Correspondence subseries includes Richardson's copies of exchanges between the editors, the contributors, and the publishers of the volume. Typically these are Richardson's email printouts, occasionally accompanied by personal notes or drafts of emails.
  - Drafts/Editing, 1996-2014; 1
    - Original manuscript Introduction, 2000 (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents note
      draft
    - Original manuscript publisher correspondence, 2000-2014 (Box 1)
      includes Judy Richardson's reflection
    - Original draft Emmie Schrader Adams, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Victoria Gray Adams, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Annie Pearl Avery, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Annie Pearl Avery, undated (Box 1)
    - Original draft Elaine DeLott Baker, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Ella Baker, undated (Box 1)
      speech excerpt
    - Contributions: Elaine DeLott Baker, 2007 (Box 1)
      correspondence
    - Original draft Debbie Amis Bell, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Debbie Amis Bell, 1996-2007 (Box 1)
      drafts and correspondence
    - Original draft Barbara Brandt, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Angeline Butler, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Angeline Butler, 2003-2007 (Box 1)
      drafts
    - Original draft Cathy Cade, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Cathy Cade, 1997-2007 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Constance Curry, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Constance Curry, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
      draft with edits
    - Original draft Peggy Dammond, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Gloria Richardson Dandridge, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Gloria Richardson Dandridge, 1998-2007 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Carolyn Daniels, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Carolyn Daniels, 2003-2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Victoria Gray Diamond, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Betty Fikes, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Joanne Grant, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Joanne Grant, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft McCree L Harris, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: McCree Harris, undated (Box 1)
    - Original draft Rutha Mae Harris, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Rutha Mae Harris, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Casey Hayden, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Casey Hayden, 1997 and 2006-2007 (Box 1)
      drafts and edits and proofs and correspondence
    - Original draft Margaret Herring, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Margaret Herring, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Faith S. Holsaert, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Faith S. Holsaert, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Gloria House, undated (Box 1)
    - Original draft E. Jeanne Breaker Johnson, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Jeanne Breaker Johnson, undated (Box 1)
      drafts and edits
    - Original draft Jeanette King, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Mary E. King, 2010 (Box 1)
      proof
    - Contributions: Joyce Ladner, 2000-2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Marilyn Lowen, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Joanne Christian Mants, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Joanne Christian Mants, 2002-2007 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Elizabeth Sutherland Martinez, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Elizabeth Sutherland Martinez, 2006 November-2007 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Jane Bond Moore, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Jane Bond Moore, 2006 (Box 1)
      draft and edits
    - Contributions: Janet Jemmott Moses, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Joan Trumpauer Mulholland, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Joan T. Mulholland, 2002-2006 (Box 1)
      edits
    - Contributions: Diane Nash, 2006 (Box 1)
      drafts notes
    - Contributions: Martha Prescod Norman Noonan, undated (Box 1)
    - Original draft Barbara Jones Omolada, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Barabara Jones Omolada, 1997-2006 (Box 1)
      edited drafts
    - Original draft Hellen O'Neal-McCray, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Hellen O'Neal-McCray, 2006-2007 (Box 1)
      draft excerpts
    - Original draft Mildred Forman Page, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Mildred Forman Page, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Penny Patch, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Gwen Patton, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Original draft Fay Bellamy (Powell), 2000 (Box 1)
    - Contributions: Fay Bellamy Powell, 2000-2007 (Box 2)
      drafts/edits
    - Contributions: Peggy T. Dammond Preacely, 1997-2003 (Box 2)
      drafts, transcripts, and correspondence
    - Original draft: Janie Culbreth Rambeau, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Janie Culbreth Rambeau, 1997-2007 (Box 2)
    - Original draft Bernice Johnson Reagon, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Bernice Reagon, 2003-2007 (Box 2)
      drafts, correspondence, proofs
    - Original draft Judy Richardson, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Judy Richardson, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
      drafts, edits
    - Contributions: Judy Richardson, 1997-2000 and undated (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Judy Richardson, 2000-2007 (Box 2)
      drafts, proofs
    - Contributions: Betty Garman Robinson, undated (Box 2)
    - Original draft Zoharah Simmons (Gwendolyn Robinson), 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Zoharah Simmons (Gwendoyln Robinson), 1997-2007 (Box 2)
      correspondence, drafts
    - Original draft Muriel Tillinghast, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Muriel Tillinghast, 1997-2006 (Box 2)
      draft, correspondence
    - Contributions: Maria Varela, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
    - Original draft Annette Jones White, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Annette Jones White, 1997-2007 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Jean Wiley, 1999 (Box 2)
      drafts with edits
    - Original draft Prathia Hall Wynn, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Prathia Hall Wynn, 1999-2003 (Box 2)
    - Original draft Jean Wheeler Smith Young, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Jean Smith Young, 1997-2010 (Box 2)
      proof, drafts, original version
    - Original draft Dorothy Zellner, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Contributions: Dorothy Zellner, 1997-2007 (Box 2)
      drafts, correspondence
    - Bridges, 2000 (Box 2)
      drafts, edits, correspondence
    - Bridges: drafts sent to Illinois University Press, Nov-07 (Box 2)
    - Bridges and Introduction drafts, 2006 November-2009 January (Box 2)
    - Introduction drafts, edits, correspondence, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
    - Introduction, Table of Contents, author bios, 2003-2007 (Box 3)
    - Revision checklists, style sheet, 2006-2007 and undated (Box 3)
    - Bridges (drafts), 2009 January (Box 3)
    - Bridges (drafts), March 2009-April 2009 (Box 3)
    - Postscript drafts, related correspondence, 2009 May (Box 3)
    - Photos: takestock, permissions, usage, etc, 2009 (Box 3)
    - Photos: hi-resolution images, permissions, correspondence, 2010 (Box 3, Cd RL10177-ECD-002, Cd RL10177-ECD-003)
    - Photos: book cover, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Photos: correspondence, edits for catptions, 2009-2010 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript draft for Oxford University Press, 2002 November 17 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript draft with Oxford University edits, suggestions, correspondence, 2002-2003 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript draft excerpt, 2002-2003 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript draft for Faith Childs Literary Agency, 2003 September 29 (Box 3)
    - Complete draft, 2005 May 19 (Box 3)
    - Electronic drafts, 2007-2009 (Cd RL10177-ECD-005, Cd RL10177-ECD-006, Cd RL10177-ECD-004, Box 3)
      Includes ECD-004 (draft from Nov. 2007); ECD-005 (draft from May 2009); ECD-006 (draft from June 2007).
    - Proofing/indexing process, 2010 (Box 3)
    - Manuscript binder part 1 of 4, undated (Box 3)
    - Manuscript binder part 2 of 4, undated (Box 3)
    - Manuscript binder part 3 of 4, undated (Box 3)
    - Manuscript binder part 4 of 4, undated (Box 3)
    - Copyediting, 2010 (Box 5)
    - JR's letter to the editor of Emerge magazine, re: Ruby Doris Robinson, 1998 (Box 5)
    - Reader comments: reader 1, 2008 November-December (Box 5)
    - Reader comments: reader 2, 2008 November (Box 5)
  - Publication, 2000-2014; 2
    - Copyright info, undated (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity, 2011 March (Box 5)
      National Museum of African American History and Culture event
    - Southern Exposure Magazine submission excerpts, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Maya Angelou invitation, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity/book events, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity/book events, 2010 (Box 5)
      University of Illinois Press
    - Marketing/publicity/book events, 2010 (Box 5)
      ASALH
    - Marketing/publicity/book events, 2010 August-October (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity/book events, 2010 October-2011 February (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity/events, 2011 March-May (Box 5)
    - Marketing/publicity/events, 2011 June-December (Dvd RL10177-EDVD-001, Box 5)
      DVD contains PowerPoint files with no captions.
    - Marketing/publicity/events, 2012-2014 (Box 5)
    - Reviews, 2010-2011 (Box 5)
    - Awards, undated (Box 5)
    - Publishing/research/book trade, 2000s (Box 5)
      clippings, excerpts, etc
  - Correspondence, 1995-2012; 3
    - Correspondence, notes, 1995-1996 (Box 4)
      early drafts
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2000-2002 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2005 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2006 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, some draft mats, 2007 (Box 4)
      emails
    - Correspondence, 2008 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2009 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 2009 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2009 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, notes, 2010 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 2010 (Box 4)
      emails, notes
    - Correspondence, notes, 2011-2012 (Box 4)
    - Marie Brown Literary Agency correspondence, draft excerpt, 1997 (Box 4)
    - Marie Brown Literary Agency correspondence, notes, 1998 (Box 4)
    - Marie Brown Literary Agency correspondence, notes, proposal, 1999-2000 (Box 4)
    - Faith Childs Literary Agency correspondence, notes, etc, 2000-2009 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence: mailings to contributors, 1996-2001 (Box 4)
    - Oxford University Press correspondence, notes, 2002 (Box 4)
    - Comments/correspondence from UNC Press, 2005 (Box 4)
- SNCC and Civil Rights Movement, 1963-1970; 1
  This series contains Richardson's original documents from the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and other civil rights organizations, including the Council of Federated Organizations (COFO) and the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party. Files are arranged into three subseries: SNCC, the Residential Freedom School, and Ralph Featherstone.
  The SNCC subseries includes newsletters, internal memoranda, and official circulars from several SNCC offices, including the national office and the New York office. The subseries contains material from various SNCC initiatives and partnerships, such as the Mississippi Summer Project, the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, civil rights conferences and demonstrations, the Julian Bond senatorial campaign, Black Panther literature, informational brochures on voter registration and organizing, and other miscellaneous printed materials. It also includes materials documenting Richardson's involvement in the Mississippi Summer Project, the campus travellers program, and the Heart of Atlanta hotel sit-in demonstration.
  The Residential Freedom School subseries includes Richardson's work on establishing, funding, and running a Residential Freedom School in Alabama during the summer of 1965. It includes correspondence, registration information, logistical and administrative files, and program evaluations for the school.
  The Death of Ralph Featherstone subseries contains documents acquired and collected by Richardson following the purported assassination of Ralph Featherstone and William "Che" Payne in Maryland. Featherstone worked with Richardson at Drum and Spear Bookstore in Washington, D.C.
  - Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), 1963-1967; 1
    - Afro Arts, undated (Box 6)
    - Mao and Black Power, undated (Box 6)
    - Memo to SNCC Staff, 1977-August-25 (Box 6)
    - Negro History Book, undated (Box 6)
    - Precinct 1 Graph with Lowndes County Freedom Organization back, undated (Box 6)
    - Paved roads petition, undated (Box 6)
    - Memo from Bill Wallace to the executive committee, undated (Box 6)
    - Letter from Lavern Lilly Neblett, 1965-November-22 (Box 6)
    - Scholarship and counseling program, undated (Box 6)
    - Report on meeting of Nov 18, Washington D.C, Nov 18 (unknown year) (Box 6)
    - A proposal for Washington studies, undated (Box 6)
    - Summer Project, undated (Box 6)
    - A comment on the institute, undated (Box 6)
    - To those interested in the struggle, undated (Box 6)
    - Happy Daze are here again, undated (Box 6)
    - Montgomery Improvement Association, 1964-October-5 (Box 6)
    - Life with Lyndon Vol.1 No. 42, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Life with Lyndon Vol.1 No. 38, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Letter by Bill Wale, undated (Box 6)
    - Housing Committee workshop, 1967 February 7-9 (Box 6)
    - Folks need each other by Mike Miller, undated (Box 6)
    - Memo to all project directors, undated (Box 6)
    - SNCC Communication, 1967-March-17 (Box 6)
    - An urgent message from NY SNCC, 1967-July-1 (Box 6)
    - To SNCC Staff, 1965-July-19 (Box 6)
    - Black Men and the draft, 1967-June-8 (Box 6)
    - Jet Magazine, "Adam Powell: Key man on capitol hill", 1965-May-13 (Box 6)
    - Peace! The World from African Eyes, 1960 September 23 (Box 6)
    - SCLC Scope project pamphlet, undated (Box 6)
    - The fighter publication, 1967-February-1 (Box 6)
    - Support east central citizens organization ECCO Pamphlet, undated (Box 6)
    - The Southern Patriot Vol 23, No.9, November65 (Box 6)
    - Public Law 88-352 88th Congress, H.R 7152, 1964-July-2 (Box 6)
    - A history of negroes in America article, undated (Box 6)
    - The razor, the official Black-Fact Organ, undated (Box 6)
    - What about Civil Rights and Barry Goldwater? Pamphlet, undated (Box 6)
    - A Special Message for Tennesseans, undated (Box 6)
    - National Afro American Student Conference on Afro Youth, 1964 October-November (Box 6)
    - A Goldwater Primer Publication, undated (Box 6)
    - Black America Publication, 1964 Fall (Box 6)
    - The Voice, Vol 6, No.6 Publication, 1965-December-20 (Box 6)
    - The Congressional record article, 1965-September-17 (Box 6)
    - Building a new Mississippi, undated (Box 6)
    - ASCS Elections, undated (Box 6)
    - Newsletter ECCO Sounding Off April 1966,Issue No. 1, 1966-April (Box 6)
    - SNCC Contact List, undated (Box 6)
    - Note about John Dunn, undated (Box 6)
    - Appointment Card for Stllman (Tuscaloosa), undated (Box 6)
    - Contact Info for Richard Brewer, undated (Box 6)
    - Contact Info for Eddie Livingston, undated (Box 6)
    - Contact info for George N. Scott, undated (Box 6)
    - undated (Box 6)
    - Handwritten Note About Tennessee A, undated (Box 6)
    - Handwritten Note on Dr. Eagle (New World), undated (Box 6)
    - Handwritten Note, Phone Messages, undated (Box 6)
    - Handwritten Note, General Contacts, undated (Box 6)
    - Handwritten Note, Interested Students, undated (Box 6)
    - Notebook, Alabama College Contacts and Schedule, undated (Box 6)
    - Notepad, Office Notes, undated (Box 6)
    - SNCC Letterhead, Blank, undated (Box 6)
    - "Will They Die" - SNCC Communications, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Brochure - "What Would It Profit a Man," A Report On Alabama, undated (Box 6)
    - "Some Provisions for Federal Prosecution in Civil Rights", undated (Box 6)
    - "Why Did Johnson Appoint a Racist Judge from Mississippi," SNCC Research, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Greene County, Alabama - Statistical Profile, undated (Box 6)
    - Background of Poor Peoples' Use of Greenville Air Force Base, undated (Box 6)
    - Delta Ministry Reports - "Greenville Airbase, What Happened and Why", 1966 (Box 6)
    - Act for Freedom Statement, undated (Box 6)
    - Cambridge Nonviolent Action Committee, RE: Cambridge Direct Action, undated (Box 6)
    - Cambridge Free Press, "Over 70 Arrested", undated (Box 6)
    - "Why Student Voice" Publication, undated (Box 6)
    - SNCC Executive Committee Meeting Notes, April 12-14, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Memo from James Foreman, RE: SNCC Financial Situation, 1965 (Box 6)
    - SNCC Complaint Against the US Government (US District Court-Southern District of New York (Box 6)
    - A Petition (To Be Submitted to Be Submitted in the Appeal of the Conviction of the Harlem Six), undated (Box 6)
    - SNCC: A Special Report On Southern School Desegregation, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Congressional Challenge - Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Vote Democratic! Flag, undated (Box 6)
    - "Discrimination" (Tarrytown for Civil Rights' improvement League of the Tarrytowners), undated (Box 6)
    - Mississippi Freedom Labor Union Report, undated (Box 6)
    - Prospectus For A Nation-Wide High School SNCC Conference, undated (Box 6)
    - COFO (Council of Federated Organizations) Letterhead, undated (Box 6)
    - The Story of the Development of an Independent Political Movement on the County Level (LCFO), undated (Box 6)
    - "A Community Servicce Project" Do It Yourself Handbook for a Volunteer Tutoring Service, undated (Box 6)